{
  "reference_number": "977",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Of the two options above, the second is slightly preferable as it allows somewhat more flexibility. A third option, in which the\n Government does not set an emissions reduction target at all, would be better still."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "If a target is indeed to be set, then the first option, being the least onerous, is the one that should be adopted. Not setting a target at\n all would be preferable."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "The second option is still a bad option but is preferable because it allows slightly more flexibility. But neither option really answers the\n question: how exactly is New Zealand going to meet its targets? The Discussion Document speaks of innovation and land use\n\n changes, but there are few details about what these may entail. There will no doubt be a move to greater levels of renewable\n electricity generation, but will this, for example, require damming more of our few remaining wild rivers? Will we still require substantial\n reserves of base load electricity generation capacity for those times when the wind doesn't blow and the sun doesn't shine, and what\n\n forms will they take? How do we power the expanding fleet of electric vehicles? If we have to reduce our livestock farming industries\n to meet targets for methane and nitrous oxide (assuming these are set), how do we fill the hole this will leave in our national\n economy?"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "2050 is 32 years away. Thirty-two years ago, in 1986, there was no internet, hardly any mobile phones, the USSR was still intact and\n the Berlin Wall still up, there was a stock market boom that was about to end in spectacular fashion, and New Zealand had double-\n digit inflation. We have no idea what the future holds, and need to retain as much flexibility as we can to face whatever it may throw at\n\n us. Furthermore, there is a significant minority of climate scientists who consider that the current level of concern about climate\n change is considerably overstated; it may yet turn out that they're right. For a paper on how the current scientific “consensus” has\n been engineered and dissenting voices suppressed for political ends, see Curry, JA and PJ Webster, 2013: Climate change: no\n\n consensus on consensus. CAB Reviews 8(1): 1-9. I have attached a copy of this (consensus-paper-revised-final.pdf, sourced from\n curryja.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/consensus-paper-revised-final.doc). A plain language version is also available at\n\n judithcurry.com/2012/10/28/climate-change-no-consensus-on-consensus In the event that the current alarm over climate change\n comes to be seen as misplaced, future generations should have the option of modifying or abandoning the course which many in\n this generation wish to set for them."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Discussion Document notes: “Setting targets is not new. New Zealand has already made commitments to reduce emissions to\n... 5 per cent below 1990 levels by 2020.” What it doesn't say is that the best we have been able to do so far, with only two years to\n\ngo until the target date, is to stabilise emissions at 19.6% above 1990 levels. Meeting these targets is likely to be very challenging\nindeed. The Document has no details on how these targets are to be enforced, and the consequences of failing to meet them are\n\nnot clear. I note Germany has just announced that it is likely to miss its goal of cutting emissions by 40 percent by 2020.\nwww.newsroom.co.nz/2018/06/19/126651/germany-will-fail-2020-climate-goals"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "See above."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If the Government is to set budgets, and if there is to be a Climate Change Commission, then these considerations are reasonable."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government's primary concern should be for the economic, social and environmental damage that actions to meet these targets\n\nmay precipitate. What would be the effect on tax revenue of restricting livestock numbers to control methane and nitrous oxide\nlevels? How would this impact the ability of the Government to support the socially disadvantaged who may, for example, require\nassistance with home heating costs in the face of higher electricity bills? What are the environmental consequences of planting fast-\n\ngrowing exotic plantation forests solely for carbon capture? The recent floods in Tolaga Bay showed the serious downstream effects\nthat can occur when forests are not properly managed; a lack of management is likely if planted trees have no clear function other\n\nthan soaking up carbon."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "A Climate Change Commission is unnecessary and diverts Government attention away from more serious matters. Some of the\nactions proposed to fight climate change (such as increasing energy efficiency, improving home insulation, better public transport\n\nand affordable housing) make sense on their own merits and should be pursued, but putting all the focus on emissions is likely to\ndistort economic signals and produce undesirable outcomes such as suppressed economic activity and more expensive energy, to\nno good purpose. The destruction of American forests to produce “biofuels” for export to Europe is an illustration of the effects this\n\nnarrow focus on “carbon neutrality” can have; we do not want to see these follies repeated in New Zealand.\nwww.businessinsider.com/europe-imports-wood-biomass-from-us-for-power-2015-12/?r=AU&IR=T"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Both are poor options: better to have no Climate Change Commission at all. But if one must be established, then it is preferable it\n\nhave an advisory capacity only."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Better to have no Climate Change Commission, but if one must be established this range of expertise looks appropriate."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "If there has to be a Zero Carbon Bill, it should be as small and unobtrusive as possible. Climate change will continue to occur\n\nregardless of what human greenhouse gas emissions may be, but its direction and extent will be impossible to predict. New Zealand\nrequires as much economic resilience as possible to deal with any future adverse events, and setting rules now will not help future\n\ngenerations to cope with situations which they will be able to perceive far more clearly than we can. Restricting economic activity and\nhence national financial resources through efforts to fight climate change will also limit the options of future generations."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The proposals would only serve to create more bureaucracy and lead to more, not less, inefficiency in the way national and local\ngovernments conduct their operations."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "See above."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please see attached document (Zero Carbon Bill Submission Supplementary Comments.pdf)"
    }
  ]
}
